Willowbrook Collection
Willowbrook Collection
circa 1972-1982
American Broadcasting Company.
7 linear ft.
Notes, videos and films relating to Geraldo Rivera's 1972 exposé of conditions at Staten Island's Willowbrook State School.
2726309
Biographical History
In 1972 television reporter and talk show host Geraldo Rivera, then a budding journalist working for WABC-New York's Eyewitness News, conducted a series of investigations at the Willowbrook State School for the Mentally Retarded, on Staten Island. His work resulted in a televised documentary entitled "Willowbrook: The Last Great Disgrace" which exposed the deplorable conditions and the rampant abuse and neglect of the residents. The report won a Peabody Award and led to changes in state law and to new standards for the treatment of the mentally disabled across the country, as well as making Rivera a national star. Willowbrook closed in 1987 and the area is now part of the campus of Staten Island College.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Willowbrook Collection consists of notes, photographs, videos, and films relating to "Willowbrook: The Last Great Disgrace." There are also a few unrelated items, such as a copy of Rivera's biography, Exposing Myself.
Other Formats Available
Portions of the collection have been digitized. Contact the repostory listed above for more information.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection remains in original order.
Related Material
Additional material relating to disability and disabled persons may be found in several other collections, including the
William Langner Papers
, the
James Pirkl Papers
, the
James Thornton Correspondence
, and the
Rowley Family Papers
, among others.
Subject and Genre Headings
Journalism; Radio, television, film; Activism and social reform; Rivera, Geraldo.; Willowbrook State School.; Willowbrook: the last great disgrace.; Investigative reporting.; Journalists -- United States.; People with disabilities -- Abuse of -- United States.; People with disabilities -- Institutional care -- United States.; 16mm (photographic film size); Betacam (TM); Notes (documents); Photographs.; Pamphlets.; Negatives (photographs); Correspondence.; Clippings (information artifacts); VHS.; Videotapes.; Journalists.; Investigative reporting.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Bernard Carabello: A Willowbrook Case in Box 8 is restricted.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Paul R. Dolan, 1993.
Inventory
- Correspondence-subject files
  - Guide to overall resources (Box 1)
  - Guide to legal resources (Box 1)
  - Guide to film and tape resources (Box 1)
  - Community acceptance resources (Box 1)
  - Investigating abuse (Box 1)
  - Clips, correspondence, 1972-1982 (Box 2)
  - Photos, Willowbrook report, WABC News (Box 2)
  - Film strips (negatives) (Box 2)
  - Willowbrook photos (Box 2)
  - ARC photos (Box 2)
  - Media awards (Box 2)
  - Concert, Chicago, 1977 (Box 2)
  - Dance Marathon, 1978-1979 (Box 2)
  - Exposing Myself, Geraldo Rivera (Box 3)
  - Community acceptance (Box 3)
  - Observing and gaining community acceptance, books and pamphlets (Box 3)
  - One to One key documents (Box 1)
  - One to One files (Box 2)
  - One to One history shots, TBE, 1 Kodak box (Box 3)
  - One to One selected home shots, miscellaneous negatives (Box 4)
    See also Recordings: One to One.
  - Center on Human Policy (Box 4)
  - How to Create Interiors for the Disabled, Jane Randolph Cary (Box 4)
  - Unequal Justice?, Robert Perske (Box 4)
  - New Neighbors, U.S. Dept. of Health and Human Services (Box 4)
  - Access, The Guide to a Better Life for the Disabled Americans, Lilly Bruck (Box 4)
  - Creating Community Acceptance for Handicapped People, Roberta Nelson (Box 4)
  - Alternatives in the community for the developmentally disabled, pamphlets and guidebooks (Box 4)
  - Bernard Carabello: A Willowbrook Case (Box 8)
    This file is temporarily restricted.
  - Syracuse (Box 4)
- Recordings
  - 20/20, Willowbrook Revisited, 6 Jan 1982; willowbrook_007; 1 Umatic tape (Box 5)
  - 20/20 TS-087 McNulty, 2 Nov 1987; willowbrook_008, willowbrook_009; 2 Umatic tapes (Box 5)
  - Channel 5 News, 10 to 11PM edition, 18 Jan 1977; willowbrook_017; report on One to One Dance Marathon; 1 Umatic tape (Box 6)
  - "Death in the Nursery", willowbrook_013; parts 1-4 (Newsbreakers report); 1 Umatic tape (Box 5)
  - Evening News, 9 Apr 1977; willowbrook_010; 1 Umatic tape (Box 5)
  - Eyewitness 12 News, 6 to 7PM edition, 18 Jan 1977; willowbrook_005; includes report on One to One Dance Marathon; 1 Umatic tape (Box 5)
  - Eyewitness News, 11:00 PM edition, 17 Jan 1977; willowbrook_006; includes report on One to One Dance Marathon; 1 Umatic tape (Box 5)
  - Good Morning America, 2 Jun 1977; willowbrook_015; Geraldo at AABR Chicago explaining One to One; 1 Umatic tape (Box 5)
  - Good Morning America, 2 Jun 1977; willowbrook_016; Geraldo at AABR Chicago explaining One to One; 1 DVD-Video (Box 5)
  - Good Morning America, 20 Jun 1977; willowbrook_012; 1 Umatic tape (Box 5)
  - Good Morning America, 14 Oct 1977; willowbrook_011; Paul Dolan and Felton King; 1 Umatic tape (Box 5)
  - One to One Telethon, 6 Jun 1979; willowbrook_019, willowbrook_020, willowbrook_021; 3 Umatic tapes (Box 6)
  - One to One Telethon, 3 Jun 1980; willowbrook_026, willowbrook_027, willowbrook_028, willowbrook_029; reels 2A, 3, 3A, 4A; 4 Umatic tapes (Box 6)
  - One to One Telethon, 24 Jun 1981; willowbrook_022, willowbrook_023, willowbrook_024, willowbrook_025; reels 1-4; 4 Umatic tapes (Box 6)
  - ROI (Residential Opportunities Inc.) Home Video, willowbrook_004; about life in group homes; 1 VHS tape (Box 1)
  - Self Advocacy: the Developmentally Disabled Speak for Themselves, willowbrook_018; 1 Umatic tape (Box 6)
  - The Willowbrook Case (WLPG-TV, Miami), willowbrook_001; 1 Betacam tape (Box 1)
  - The Willowbrook Case (WLPG-TV, Miami), willowbrook_002, willowbrook_003; 2 VHS tapes (Box 1)
  - Willowbrook: The Case, willowbrook_030; original film can had label, "ABC News 20/20"; 16mm film, 1 reel (Box 7)
  - Yes You Can, willowbrook_014; story of Timmy Loughlin, Down syndrome child; 1 videotape (Box 5)